<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Tutorial | Paul Liautaud</title><link>https://paulliautaud.github.io/tag/tutorial/</link><atom:link href="https://paulliautaud.github.io/tag/tutorial/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Tutorial</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://paulliautaud.github.io/media/icon_hu5a8bb89b166067dad42de6c6e5349de5_15995_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Tutorial</title><link>https://paulliautaud.github.io/tag/tutorial/</link></image><item><title>Chapter 0 - Preliminaries</title><link>https://paulliautaud.github.io/teaching/python/00_preliminaries/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://paulliautaud.github.io/teaching/python/00_preliminaries/</guid><description>&lt;p>This section will first present what Python is. Then, it will show and demistify the main steps to set Python and Anaconda environment on any laptop.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="first-why-python-">First, why Python ?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Python is a general-purpose interpreted programming language which has the particularity of being very readable and pragmatic.
It has a very large base of external modules, especially scientific ones, which makes it particularly attractive for programming mathematical problems.
The fact that Python is an interpreted language makes it slower than compiled languages, but on the other hand it ensures a great speed of development which allows the human to work a little less while the computer will have to work a little more.
This particularity has made Python one of the main programming languages used by scientists.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="prerequisites">Prerequisites&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The prerequisite would be to know the basics of the Python language, for example as taught in the last year&amp;rsquo;s course.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>People who are not familiar with the basics of the Python language should take the MOOC (Massive Open Online Course) &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://www.fun-mooc.fr/fr/cours/python-3-des-fondamentaux-aux-concepts-avances-du-langage/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Python 3 : des fondamentaux aux concepts avancés du langage&lt;/a>&lt;/em> available on the website of &lt;a href="https://www.fun-mooc.fr/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">France Université Numérique&lt;/a>.
In case access is restricted, the videos of the MOOC are available on &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCIlUBOXnXjxdjmL_atU53kA/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouTube&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition, the realization of the exercises requires access to a computer or an online service with Python 3.6 (or more recent) completed by the following modules: &lt;code>numpy&lt;/code>, &lt;code>scipy&lt;/code>, &lt;code>sympy&lt;/code>, &lt;code>matplotlib&lt;/code>, &lt;code>numba&lt;/code>, &lt;code>networkx&lt;/code> and &lt;code>pandas&lt;/code>. The use of a code editor allowing writing in Python is also highly recommended. It is suggested here to use &lt;a href="https://jupyterlab.readthedocs.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jupyter Lab&lt;/a>, which allows both writing interactive notebooks and scripts and also adding one&amp;rsquo;s own solutions below the statements, which is very convenient. It is not necessary to use Jupyter Lab, other environments are also suitable, such as &lt;a href="https://www.spyder-ide.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Spyder&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://jupyter-notebook.readthedocs.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jupyter Notebook&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following sections describe how to install and run the Python environment or use it online without installation.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="documentation">Documentation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It is generally not useful (nor desirable) to know all the functions and subtleties of the Python language for occasional use. On the other hand, it is essential to know how to use the documentation effectively. The official documentation is available at &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://docs.python.org/&lt;/a>. The language and version can be selected on the top left. It is highly recommended to look at how the documentation is written and learn how to use it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="installation">Installation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Those unable or unwilling to install Python can go directly to the &lt;a href="#sec:intro-lancement">1.5 Launching Jupyter Lab&lt;/a> section for alternatives available online without installation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are essentially four ways to install Python and the modules required to run the exercises:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Anaconda&lt;/strong> is a complete Python distribution, i.e. it directly installs a very large quantity of modules (much more than we actually need). The advantage of this installation is that it is very simple; the disadvantage is that it takes up a lot of disk space. This is the preferred method if you are running Windows or MacOS and do not have disk space problems.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Miniconda&lt;/strong> is a light version of Anaconda, which installs only the base by default. The advantage is that it takes up little disk space, but it requires an additional action to install the modules needed. This is the preferred method if you are on Windows or MacOS and have little disk space available.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Linux repositories:&lt;/strong> Most Linux distributions allow you to install Python and the basic modules directly from the package repositories that come with them. This is the preferred method under Linux.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Pip&lt;/strong> is a package manager for Python. This is the preferred method to add a module if Python is already installed by your operating system, and this module is not included in the packages of your distribution. This method allows a more fine and advanced management of installed modules than what is proposed with the previous methods.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="installation-with-anaconda">Installation with Anaconda&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The easiest way to install Python 3 and all necessary dependencies on Windows and MacOS is to install &lt;a href="https://anaconda.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Anaconda&lt;/a>. The disadvantage of Anaconda is that it takes a lot of disk space to install because so many modules are installed by default. Detailed installation procedures according to each operating system are described at: &lt;a href="https://docs.anaconda.com/anaconda/install/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://docs.anaconda.com/anaconda/install/&lt;/a>. In summary the installation procedure is as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Download Anaconda for Python 3 at: &lt;a href="https://www.anaconda.com/products/individual#Downloads" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.anaconda.com/products/individual#Downloads&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Double-click on the downloaded file to start the installation of Anaconda, then follow the installation procedure (it is not necessary to install VS Code).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Once the installation is complete, launch Anaconda Navigator from the start menu or from the list of applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="installation-with-miniconda">Installation with Miniconda&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>La distribution &lt;a href="https://docs.conda.io/miniconda.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Miniconda&lt;/a> présente l&amp;rsquo;avantage sur Anaconda de prendre peu d&amp;rsquo;espace disque, au prix de devoir installer les modules nécessaires manuellement. La procédure d&amp;rsquo;installation rapide est la suivante:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Télécharger Miniconda pour Python 3 à l&amp;rsquo;adresse: &lt;a href="https://docs.conda.io/miniconda.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://docs.conda.io/miniconda.html&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Double-cliquer sur le fichier téléchargé pour lancer l&amp;rsquo;installation de Miniconda, puis suivre la procédure d&amp;rsquo;installation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Une fois l&amp;rsquo;installation terminée, lancer Anaconda Prompt à partir du menu Démarrer ou de la liste des applications.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dans le terminal, taper la commande:
conda install anaconda-navigator numpy scipy sympy matplotlib numba networkx pandas jupyterlab
et confirmer l&amp;rsquo;installation des dépendances.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="installation-à-partir-des-dépôts">Installation à partir des dépôts&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>La plupart des distributions Linux permettent d&amp;rsquo;installer facilement Python et les modules les plus standard directement à partir des dépôts qu&amp;rsquo;elles incluent. La procédure suivante concerne Ubuntu, mais s&amp;rsquo;adapte facilement aux autres distributions.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Installer Python 3:
sudo apt install python3 python-pip3&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Installer les modules &lt;code>numpy&lt;/code>, &lt;code>scipy&lt;/code>, &lt;code>sympy&lt;/code>, &lt;code>matplotlib&lt;/code>, &lt;code>numba&lt;/code>, &lt;code>networkx&lt;/code> et &lt;code>pandas&lt;/code>:
sudo apt install python3-numpy python3-scipy python3-sympy python3-matplotlib python3-numba python3-networkx python3-pandas&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jupyter Lab n&amp;rsquo;étant pas disponible dans les paquets d&amp;rsquo;Ubuntu, il faut l&amp;rsquo;installer avec Pip:
pip3 install jupyterlab&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Remarque:&lt;/strong>
Suivant les systèmes d&amp;rsquo;exploitation il faut parfois remplacer la commande &lt;code>pip3&lt;/code> par &lt;code>pip&lt;/code>. Si vous rencontrez un problème de permissions lors de l&amp;rsquo;exécution de ces commandes, il faut probablement rajouter &lt;code>--user&lt;/code> à la fin de la commande précédente.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="installation-avancée-avec-pip">Installation avancée avec Pip&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>La procédure suivante décrit l&amp;rsquo;installation manuelle de modules avec le gestionnaire &lt;a href="https://pip.pypa.io/en/stable/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pip&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Installer Python depuis l&amp;rsquo;adresse: &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/downloads/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.python.org/downloads/&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Installer Pip depuis l&amp;rsquo;adresse: &lt;a href="https://pip.pypa.io/en/stable/installation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://pip.pypa.io/en/stable/installation/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Installer les modules requis en tapant la ligne de commande suivante dans un terminal:
pip3 install numpy scipy sympy matplotlib numba networkx pandas jupyterlab
&lt;strong>Remarque:&lt;/strong>
Suivant les systèmes d&amp;rsquo;exploitation il faut remplacer la commande &lt;code>pip3&lt;/code> par &lt;code>pip&lt;/code>. Si vous rencontrez un problème de permissions lors de l&amp;rsquo;exécution de ces commandes, il faut probablement rajouter &lt;code>--user&lt;/code> à la fin de la commande précédente.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h1 id="15-lancement-de-jupyter-lab">1.5 Lancement de Jupyter Lab&lt;/h1>
&lt;div id="sec:intro-lancement">&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="avec-anaconda-navigator">Avec Anaconda Navigator&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Si Anaconda ou Miniconda a été installé, il suffit de lancer Anaconda Navigator et de cliquer sur l&amp;rsquo;icône «jupyterlab»:&lt;/p>
&lt;center>&lt;img src="https://python.guillod.org/fig/anaconda.png" style="width:90%;max-width:900px;">&lt;/center>
&lt;h3 id="en-ligne-de-commande">En ligne de commande&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Pour lancer Jupyter Lab en ligne de commande, il faut taper &lt;code>jupyter lab&lt;/code> dans un terminal. Pour quitter, il faut cliquer sur «Shutdown» dans le menu «File» de la fenêtre Jupyter Lab. Il est aussi possible de taper &lt;code>Ctrl+C&lt;/code> suivi de &lt;code>y&lt;/code> (en anglais) ou &lt;code>o&lt;/code> (en français) dans le terminal où la commande &lt;code>jupyter lab&lt;/code> a été exécutée.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sur-le-bureau-de-lutes">Sur le bureau de l&amp;rsquo;UTES&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Avertissement:&lt;/strong>
Disponible seulement pour les personnes disposant d&amp;rsquo;un accès informatique à Sorbonne Université.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Aller sur le site de l&amp;rsquo;&lt;a href="https://lutes.upmc.fr/bdl-ext.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UTES&lt;/a> puis cliquer sur l&amp;rsquo;icône correspondante à votre système d&amp;rsquo;exploitation et suivez les instructions pour vous connecter au bureau à distance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pour lancer Jupyter Lab une fois connecté au bureau de l&amp;rsquo;UTES:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>cliquer sur la loupe située en haut;&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>taper &lt;code>jupyter lab&lt;/code> dans le champs de rechercher suivi de la touche &lt;code>ENTRÉE&lt;/code>;&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>cliquer sur «JUPYTER LAB POUR PYTHON 3.6»;&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>ne pas fermer la fenêtre noire avant d&amp;rsquo;avoir terminé de travailler sous Jupyter Lab.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="en-ligne-sans-installation">En ligne sans installation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Pour les personnes ne pouvant ou ne voulant pas installer Python et les dépendances nécessaires sur leur propre ordinateur et n&amp;rsquo;ayant pas accès au bureau de l&amp;rsquo;UTES, il est possible d&amp;rsquo;utiliser Jupyter Lab en ligne avec GESIS en cliquant &lt;a href="https://notebooks.gesis.org/binder/v2/gh/guillod/python/master?urlpath=lab/tree/chap01.ipynb" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ici&lt;/a>.
Aucun compte n&amp;rsquo;est nécessaire mais les documents stockés sans compte utilisateur sont automatiquement effacés donc il faut impérativement les sauvegarder sur votre propre ordinateur avant de quitter. Il est également possible de créer un compte utilisateur sur GESIS à l&amp;rsquo;adresse &lt;a href="https://notebooks.gesis.org/hub/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://notebooks.gesis.org/hub/&lt;/a>, ce qui permet ensuite de sauvegarder vos documents. Une fois authentifié sur GESIS, entrer les paramètres suivants pour avoir accès aux énoncés des exercices:&lt;/p>
&lt;center>&lt;img src="https://python.guillod.org/fig/gesis.png" style="width:90%;max-width:900px;">&lt;/center>
&lt;p>Pour utiliser Jupyter Lab plutôt que Jupyter Nootebook sur GESIS, il suffit de remplacer &lt;code>tree&lt;/code> par &lt;code>lab&lt;/code> à la fin de l&amp;rsquo;URL.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sinon différents services offrent la possibilité d&amp;rsquo;utiliser gratuitement Jupyter Lab après création d&amp;rsquo;un compte:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://cocalc.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CoCalc&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://colab.research.google.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google Colaboratory&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="16-utilisation-de-jupyter-lab">1.6 Utilisation de Jupyter Lab&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Une fois Jupyter Lab lancé, la fenêtre suivante doit apparaître dans un navigateur:&lt;/p>
&lt;center>&lt;img src="https://python.guillod.org/fig/jupyter.png" style="width:90%;max-width:900px;">&lt;/center>
&lt;p>Jupyter Lab permet essentiellement de traiter trois types de documents: les &lt;strong>notebooks&lt;/strong>, les &lt;strong>scripts&lt;/strong> et les &lt;strong>terminaux&lt;/strong>. Un notebook est constitué de cellules qui peuvent contenir soit du code soit du texte au format Markdown. Les cellules peuvent être évaluées de manière interactive à la demande, ce qui permet une grande flexibilité. Un script Python est simplement un fichier texte contenant des instructions Python. Il s&amp;rsquo;exécute en entier de A à Z et il n&amp;rsquo;est pas possible d&amp;rsquo;interagir interactivement avec lui pendant son exécution (à moins que cela n&amp;rsquo;ait été explicitement programmé). Pour exécuter un script python il est nécessaire d&amp;rsquo;ouvrir un terminal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Un notebook est composé de cellules, ces dernières pouvant être principalement de deux types: des cellules de code et des cellules de texte, comme représenté sur la figure suivante.
Les cellules de texte peuvent contenir des formules LaTeX.&lt;/p>
&lt;center>&lt;img src="https://python.guillod.org/fig/jupyterlab.png" style="width:90%;max-width:900px;">&lt;/center>
&lt;p>La documentation détaillée de Jupyter Lab est disponible &lt;a href="https://jupyterlab.readthedocs.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ici&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Commandes de base:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Créer un nouveau fichier: cliquer sur le bouton &lt;code>PLUS&lt;/code> situé en haut à gauche, puis choisir le type de fichier à créer.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Renommer un fichier: cliquer avec le second bouton de la souris sur le titre du notebook (soit dans l&amp;rsquo;onglet, soit dans la liste des fichiers).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Changer le type de cellules: menu déroulant permettant de choisir entre «Code» et «Markdown».&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Exécuter une cellule: combinaison des touches &lt;code>SHIFT+ENTRÉE&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Exécuter un script: taper &lt;code>python nomduscript.py&lt;/code> dans un terminal pour exécuter le script &lt;code>nomduscript.py&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Réorganiser les cellules: cliquer-déposer.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Juxtaposer des onglets: cliquer-déposer.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Remerciements:&lt;/strong> Merci à Johann Faouzi, Nicolas Lantos et Marie Postel pour leurs relectures attentives de ce recueil et pour les nombreuses corrections et suggestions. Merci également à Cédric Boutillier, Cindy Guichard et Raphaël Zanella pour avoir pointé différentes erreurs.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>